{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Evidence from the Bradford Letter argues that a performance of Cato in this location was a lavish social event, not a celebration of republicanism. In this location, a manual nicknamed the Blue Book was translated into English. Christopher Ludwick developed a type of Pepper Pot Soup at this location, where Baron von Steuben led training drills. For ten points, name this Pennsylvania location where the Continental Army spent the harsh 1777-1778 winter.",
      "answer": "Valley Forge"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was forced into exile after Publius Clodius Pulcher passed a law targeting those who executed Roman citizens without trial. He rose to prominence by successfully prosecuting Gaius Verres. As consul, he exposed the Catiline Conspiracy to the Senate and was awarded the title Pater Patriae. For ten points, name this politician, a staunch supporter of the Roman Republic and notable orator who opposed Mark Antony with his Philippics.",
      "answer": "Marcus Tullius Cicero"
    },
    {
      "question": "The third stanza of this poem describes the image of a horse wading a river around a steadfast stone. The speaker of this poem twice notes his use of “polite meaningless words” in conversation. Three stanzas of this poem close with the words “a terrible beauty is born.” The speaker references MacDonagh, MacBride, Connolly and Pearse, who were executed by the British. For ten points, name this poem by William Butler Yeats that commemorates the leaders of a failed Irish uprising.",
      "answer": "”Easter, 1916”"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man appointed the British “White Rat,” Bob Astles, as head of his anti-corruption unit. He renamed the presidential home “the command post” and instituted the State Research Bureau secret police. This man was overthrown after attempting to seize the region of Kagera from Tanzania. Earlier, this successor of Milton Obote and suspected cannibal expelled all Asians from his country. For ten points, name this dictator of Uganda from 1971 to 1979.",
      "answer": "Idi Amin Dada"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man secretly negotiated with Karl Wolff in Operation Sunrise. According to legend, after a failure by this man’s organization, JFK wanted to “splinter [it] into a thousand pieces and scatter it into the winds.” This member of the Warren Commission organized a coup with Kermit Roosevelt that sought to oust Mohammad Mosaddegh in Iran. The Bay of Pigs invasion was plotted by, for ten points, what Director of the CIA under Eisenhower and Kennedy?",
      "answer": "Allen Welsh Dulles"
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. The central figure of this controversy cried “Is there an epidemic of cholera or something?” and “What is it, do you have rocket launching pads there?” before trying to explain “This is the situation I am in – your guest.” This controversy was the fault of the Los Angeles Police, who were supposedly unable to guarantee that guest’s security while his wife, Nina, and his children were to visit “Main Street, USA” and ride the spinning teacups. For ten points, name this 1959 foreign relations gaffe in which the visiting Soviet premier was denied a visit to the “Happiest Place on Earth,” a California theme park.",
      "answer": [
        "Nikita Khrushchev being denied a trip to Disneyland",
        "answers that mention Khrushchev visiting/not being allowed to visit the Disney theme park, but"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This city hosted a 1935 exposition which featured the Richard Requa designed Old Globe Theatre. In 1995, Shawn Nelson was arrested after stealing a tank from an armory in this city. This city’s Miramar neighborhood was the original home of the Navy’s TOPGUN program. The USS Midway Museum is located in this city, across from the resort town of Coronado. Balboa Park is located in, for ten points, what Southern California city that borders Chula Vista and Tijuana?",
      "answer": "San Diego"
    },
    {
      "question": "This was the site of a massacre perpetrated by Yamaji Motoharu following victory at the Battle of Lushunkou. In a later conflict, this location was the site of a poorly executed night attack that managed to only disable the Pallada and Retvizan. Togo Heihachiro planned a surprise attack on this location in an attempt to destroy Oskar Stark’s Pacific Fleet on the second day of a war. For ten points, what Manchurian harbor was attacked to mark the beginning of the Russo-Japanese War?",
      "answer": [
        "Port Arthur or Lushun City",
        "Port",
        "Ryojun",
        "Lushunkou"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This woman’s husband died 18 days after she did, allegedly refusing to eat out of grief. This rival of Lilian Smith was left partially paralyzed after a train accident in Lexington, North Carolina. Frank Butler married this woman after she defeated him in a competition involving 25 targets. Her talent was discovered at age 8 when she downed a squirrel with a bullet to the head. For ten points, name this prominent American sharpshooter, nicknamed “Little Sure Shot” as a member of Buffalo Bill’s Wild West Show.",
      "answer": "Annie Oakley or Phoebe Anne Mosey"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event was presaged by an Emily Hobhouse “open letter” that asked “is it not our mission to preserve life?” A similar-but-unsuccessful attempt at this event was Benedict XV’s [fifteenth’s] “Truce of God.” A football game at Messines was speculated to have taken place during this event, whose participants crossed No Man’s Land to sing songs and swap rations with each other instead of bullets. For ten points, name this festive event during the winter of 1914 in which German and Allied forces stopped fighting.",
      "answer": [
        "Christmas ceasefire of World War I",
        "descriptions of a truce",
        "any sort of pause in fighting on Christmas 1914"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This government created a service of inspectors called metsuke to investigate corruption. Prior to the rule of this government, its second ruler disobeyed orders and fought the Sanada clan at Ueda Castle [oo-AY-da “castle”]. It created a policy of alternate attendance between the central court and the domains of each provincial lord. Until the Convention of Kanagawa, this government limited trade with China and Europe to the port city of Nagasaki via the sakoku law. Ieyasu founded, for ten points, what final Japanese shogunate that ruled until the Meiji Restoration?",
        "answer": [
          "Tokugawa Shogunate or Tokugawa Bakufu",
          "Edo Bakufu",
          "Shogunate",
          "Tokugawa",
          "Edo period, era, etc."
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The aforementioned fighting at Ueda Castle came during this battle in 1600, which led to Ishida Mitsunari’s capture and execution. It marked the decline of the Toyotomi clan and the beginning of the Tokugawa Shogunate.",
        "answer": "Battle of Sekigahara"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After the success of one of this group’s efforts, George Besanc¸on wrote that they had “completely dissipated all doubts.” Henry Toulmin helped attain a patent for this group, who were assisted by mechanic Charlie Taylor. This group used a forward elevator in their design of a machine that maintained three-axis control during testing near sand dunes in the Kill Devil Hills. For ten points, name this duo who, in 1903 near Kitty Hawk, achieved the first sustained flight.",
        "answer": [
          "the Wright brothers",
          "Orville and Wilbur Wright"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The success of the Wright Brothers has triggered a feud between these two states over who deserves credit as the “birthplace of aviation:” one for the site where the design was made, and the other where the flight took place. Name both states.",
        "answer": [
          "Ohio and North Carolina",
          "in either order"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In a Nikos Kazantzakis novel, this figure meets Vladimir Lenin, Don Quixote and Jesus before sailing to Antarctica. According to another work, this hero and Diomedes jump Dolon at night to extract military information; before going off to fight, this man’s son is thrown in front of a plow to prove his sanity. The plot of a wooden horse is devised by, for ten points, what king of Ithaca and clever hero of the Trojan War whose trip home is described in a Homeric epic?",
        "answer": [
          "Odysseus",
          "Ulysses"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In his early career, this Roman politician told Polybius to stop acting so much like Odysseus; as it was an early speech, it differs from this man’s later speeches and does not end with the declaration “Carthago delenda est.”",
        "answer": [
          "Cato the Elder",
          "Cato the Censor, the Wise,",
          "the Ancient"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This campaign began with an attack on the post office at Westerplatte. Army groups Pomorze and Poznany were destroyed in the Battle of Bzura during this campaign, in which Marshal Smigly-Ridz called for a retreat to the Romanian Bridgehead. This campaign, which included a false flag attack on a radio station at Gliewitz, benefited from a Soviet invasion as part of the Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact. For ten points, name this invasion that began on September 1, 1939, beginning World War II.",
        "answer": [
          "Nazi German invasion of Poland or Nazi German invasion of Poland",
          "Fall Weiss"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Elgar’s “Pomp and Circumstance” March is traditionally played at the “Last Night of” this annual British concert series. It changed venues to Royal Albert Hall after Queen’s Hall was bombed by the Germans.",
        "answer": [
          "The BBC Proms",
          "the Henry Wood Promenade Concerts"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After his wife sprained her ankle, this man cancelled his booking for a suite on the Titanic. This man inherited the whiskey manufacturer Old Overholt from his grandfather. This friend and business partner of Andrew Mellon was stabbed four times in the leg with a steel file during an assassination attempt conducted by Alexander Berkman; that event occurred after this man threatened to evict workers who participated in the 1892 Homestead Strike. For ten points, name this founder of an eponymous coke business and chairman of Carnegie Steel.",
        "answer": "Henry Clay Frick"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Frick was one of the co-founders of the South Fork Fishing and Hunting Club, a group whose poor maintenance of their property caused this 1889 disaster.",
        "answer": "Johnstown Flood"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country experienced the Beeldenstorm and was formed by the Act of Abjuration. Louis XIV invaded this country during the Disaster Year, resulting in the lynching of Cornelis and Johan de Witt. This country’s independence war started after the capture of Brill by Sea Beggars, and the Duke of Alba convened the Council of Blood in this country. This country’s revolt against Philip II of Spain was first led by William the Silent, a member of the House of Orange. For ten points, name this country of seven United Provinces with capital at Amsterdam.",
        "answer": [
          "the Netherlands or the Dutch Republic",
          "United Provinces",
          "Seven Provinces before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Johan and Cornelis de Witt governed the Netherlands during the First Period without this position, the de facto head of state for the Dutch Republic. It was typically held by members of the House of Orange.",
        "answer": "stadtholder"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This discipline is studied in a sociological way by David Bloor, which argues against its ANT theory. Paul Feyeraband developed a theory of “epistemological anarchism” in describing this discipline. The problem of induction is often studied by philosophers studying this topic to analyze the validity of its findings. Martin Gardner advocated for a “I know it when I see it” standard when discussing how to find false versions of this practice, such as phrenology and homeopathy. For ten points, name this process of organizing knowledge in the form of testable hypotheses and predictions.",
        "answer": [
          "science",
          "word forms"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Karl Popper developed this criteria for identifying the validity of a given scientific proposition. It requires that the result be possible to prove wrong.",
        "answer": [
          "falsifiability",
          "word forms"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Woodrow Wilson",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Global conflict Wilson “kept us out of,” according to his re-election campaign.",
          "answer": [
            "World War I or the Great War",
            "the War to End All Wars"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Diplomatic body that Wilson’s 14 Points called for after that conflict ended. It was replaced by the UN.",
          "answer": "League of Nations"
        },
        {
          "question": "Constitutionally-prescribed annual speech that, since Wilson, is traditionally delivered in person to Congress.",
          "answer": "State of the Union address"
        },
        {
          "question": "Film that Wilson screened at the White House and inspired the KKK’s 20th century revival.",
          "answer": "The Birth of a Nation"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cabinet position held under Wilson by A. Mitchell Palmer, who raided leftists during the Red Scare.",
          "answer": "Attorney General"
        },
        {
          "question": "Progressive political economist whose Progress and Poverty proposed a “single tax” on land that Wilson championed.",
          "answer": "Henry George"
        },
        {
          "question": "Alabama representative who names a 1913 Revenue Act, lowering tariff rates during Wilson’s presidency.",
          "answer": [
            "Oscar Underwood",
            "Underwood Tariff"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Ambassador to the Ottoman Empire who tried to stop the Armenian genocide after funding Wilson’s campaign.",
          "answer": "Henry Morgenthau, Sr."
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Tennis Court Oath",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Medieval system of vassals and lords abolished two months after its signing.",
          "answer": "feudalism"
        },
        {
          "question": "Year in which it was signed, during the very early days of the French Revolution.",
          "answer": "1789"
        },
        {
          "question": "Estate that signed the pact, unlike the clergy and aristocrats.",
          "answer": [
            "Third Estate",
            "National Assembly"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "French royal house in power at the time of its signing.",
          "answer": "House of Bourbon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Artist of The Lictors Bring to Brutus the Bodies of His Sons who created an incomplete painting based on the oath.",
          "answer": "Jacques-Louis David"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who opposed its ideals after becoming Chief Minister to Louis XVI a month after it was signed.",
          "answer": "Jacques Necker"
        },
        {
          "question": "Noble who led the oath’s delegates and future Jacobin who was born Honor´e Gabriel Riqueti.",
          "answer": "Comte de Mirabeau"
        },
        {
          "question": "Author of the oath, a Catholic abb´e who earlier asked “What is [the aforementioned Estate]?” in an influential pamphlet.",
          "answer": "Emmanuel Joseph Siey`es or Abb´e Siey`es"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Early Islam",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Empire nearly conquered by Arabs in the 6th and 7th centuries after they laid siege to Constantinople.",
          "answer": "Byzantine Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "Region that fell under Islamic control after the fall of the Sassanid Dynasty.",
          "answer": "Persia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Number of Rightly Guided Caliphs, the rulers after the death of Muhammad and before the rule of Al-Hasan.",
          "answer": "four"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last of the Rightly Guided Caliphs, who is regarded as the rightful successor of Muhammad by Shi’ites.",
          "answer": "Ali ibn Abi Talib"
        },
        {
          "question": "Arabic term, meaning “Rightly Guided,” that names the caliphate that was succeeded by the Umayyads.",
          "answer": "Rashidun Caliphate"
        },
        {
          "question": "Arabic term for an Islamic civil war. The first of these happened after the death of the caliph Uthman.",
          "answer": "Fitna"
        },
        {
          "question": "November 656 battle in which Muhammad’s wife A’isha revolted against Uthman’s successor, starting that first Islamic civil war.",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of the Camel or the Battle of Jamal",
            "the Battle of Bassorah"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "General for the Islamic armies that united Arabia after the death of Muhammad. This “Sword of Allah” captured Damascus and Jerusalem.",
          "answer": "Khalid ibn al-Walid"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this battle, the XII Corps [twelfth “core”] under Barthelemy Lebrun blocked off several streets in Bazeilles [bah-zay-uh]. During this battle, a cavalry charge on the town of Floing injured General Margueritte, and command passed to General (20 pts)",
        "Ducrot [do-crow] after one commander was wounded. The Army of Chˆalons under MacMahon attacked the Third Army and Army of the Meuse in this battle, in which (10 pts)",
        "Chassepot [shass-poh] rifles and Krupp artillery were used. General von Moltke won this battle, sealing enemy forces in Metz and capturing Napoleon III. For ten points, name this decisive battle of the Franco-Prussian War."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Sedan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the 1960’s, a mathematician from this country proved a theorem stating that sufficiently large even numbers can either be written as the sum of two primes or a prime and a semiprime. In 2014, a mathematician born in this country won the MacArthur Award for establishing the first bound on (20 pts)",
        "prime gaps. A theorem guaranteeing that a pair of modular congruence relations with coprime moduli will have solutions was discovered in this country in the third century. (10 pts)",
        "Pascal’s triangle was discovered by mathematicians in this country centuries before Pascal’s work. For ten points, name this country whose namesake “remainder theorem” was discovered by Sunzi."
      ],
      "answer": "China"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A speech during this event concluded “We are robbers, or we must be conquerors!” Ezekiel Merritt helped organize this event, at which Henry Ford led troops to victory at the Battle of Olu´mpali. In the aftermath of this event, William Todd used blackberry juice to create a (20 pts)",
        "design on a piece of brown cloth. William Ide created a manifesto during this event, which included the capture of (10 pts)",
        "Sonoma. In its aftermath, many members ended up joining a John Fremont-led battalion to fight in the Mexican-American War. For ten points, name this 1846 revolt against the Mexican government in California."
      ],
      "answer": "Bear Flag Revolt"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Dozens of ethnic Uyghurs were arrested in this city’s district of Zeytinburnu for alleged connections to Abdulkadir Masharipov’s shooting attack of the Reina night club on New Year’s Day 2017. In 2016, a leader gave a speech in this city blaming “those in (20 pts)",
        "Pennsylvania” for threatening his power. 45 people were killed after an ISIS attack on this city’s airport in June 2016. This city’s Fatih Sultan Mehmet and (10 pts)",
        "Bosphorus Bridges were closed during a July 2016 coup attempt against President Recep Tayyip Erdogan [AIRD-oh-wan]. For ten points, name this largest city in Turkey."
      ],
      "answer": "Istanbul"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader’s policies were based on a research paper of Emilio Sanfuentes known as El Ladrillo, or “the brick.” This leader used a car bombing in Washington D.C. to eliminate the ambassador Orlando Letelier. The (20 pts)",
        "Rettig Report investigated the excesses of this man and was compiled by his successor, Patricio Aylwin. This man’s DINA secret police spearheaded the Operation (10 pts)",
        "Condor campaign to disappear political dissidents, and he liberalized his economy with the help of the Chicago Boys. For ten points, name this CIA-backed Chilean dictator who overthrew Salvador Allende in 1973."
      ],
      "answer": "Augusto Pinochet"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Two men thought to be August Heinrich and a self portrait of the artist contemplate this object in a painting by Caspar David Friedrich. The scientifically accurate depiction of this object by Ludovico Cigoli and Adam Elsheimer as (20 pts)",
        "rough rather than smooth is thought to be influenced by the Sidereus Nuncius of Galileo. This object was photographed partially obscured rising over (10 pts)",
        "Half Dome in Yosemite National Park by Ansel Adams. For ten points, name this object which Vincent van Gogh showed as a yellow crescent in his Starry Night."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Earth’s moon",
        "Luna"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This president supported a bill that would have enforced the Fifteenth Amendment in the South; that Federal Elections Bill was drafted by Henry Cabot Lodge. During this man’s presidency, a sailor spat on a photo of Arturo Prat in (20 pts)",
        "Chile, sparking a bar brawl in which two sailors from the USS Baltimore were killed. William McKinley passed his namesake tariff during this man’s presidency as a member of the (10 pts)",
        "Billion Dollar Congress, which also passed the Sherman Antitrust Act in 1890. For ten points, name this US president who served between Grover Cleveland’s terms."
      ],
      "answer": "Benjamin Harrison"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Yegor Ligachev’s insults prompted this man to write a resignation letter; well after, Ligachev famously noted that this man “was wrong.” In an attempt to avoid enriching his country’s mafia and bureaucrats, this leader implemented a voucher system to sell (20 pts)",
        "state-run enterprises, but most people sold their vouchers off. This man agreed to the Belavezha Accords, establishing the Commonwealth of (10 pts)",
        "Independent States. In 1991, this man stood on top of a tank to denounce a revolt led by the KGB, shortly before he replaced Mikhail Gorbachev in power. For ten points, name this first post-Soviet President of Russia."
      ],
      "answer": "Boris Yeltsin"
    }
  ]
}